# **Dr Sonia Boender**

# **CURRICULUM VITAE**

Full name: Dr Tamara Sonia BOENDER

Gender: female (she/her)

Country of origin/nationality: the Netherlands/Dutch Languages: English (C2), German (C1), Dutch (C2, native)

E-mail: BoenderS@rki.de

Personal website: <u>www.soniaboender.com</u>

Twitter: @SoniaBoender #SoMe4epi



# **SUMMARY**

Health scientist and field epidemiologist, with a current focus on infodemic management.

Ten years of work experience (public, not-for-profit, academia), specialized in infectious diseases monitoring & surveillance and public health, on national and international level (including ECDC, WHO).

Thrives in an international, multi-disciplinary team. Independent, flexible, creative, enthusiastic, connector.

#### **SKILLS HIGHLIGHT**

- Epidemiology and public health research
- Strong communicator, infodemic manager
- Project management and organisational skills
- Experienced teacher, trainer, and mentor

#### **EDUCATION**

Charité - Universtätsmedizin & Berlin School of Public Health, Germany MSc Applied Epidemiology 2021

#### **University of Amsterdam, the Netherlands**

PhD Global Health 2016

# Liverpool School of Tropical Medicine, UK

PgCert International Public Health 2012 (with distinction)

# **VU University Amsterdam, the Netherlands**

MSc Health Sciences - Infectious Diseases and Public Health 2011 BSc General Health Sciences 2010

# **EXPERIENCE**

### **Robert Koch Institute (RKI)**

September 2018 - present, Berlin, Germany

Research Associate - Project group: Risk & Science Communication (April 2022 - present)

Supervisor: Dr Christina Leuker

- Implementing infodemic management, with a focus on social listening
- Social media communications (Twitter @rki\_de @RKI\_fuer\_Euch; Instagram @RKI\_fuer\_Euch)
- Field epidemiology training: ECDC EPIET fellow supervision, TEPHINET member of Alumni Needs Working Group

Research Associate - Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology, Surveillance Unit (Sept. 2020 - April 2022)

Supervisor: Ms Michaela Diercke

- Surveillance of notifiable infectious diseases in Germany
- Project coordinator, setting up a syndromic surveillance system based on routine emergency department data of >30 clinics in Germany
- Supporting the COVID-19 outbreak response in Germany
- Weekly involvement in RKIs social media communications
- Field epidemiology training: ECDC EPIET fellow supervision, TEPHINET member of Alumni Needs Working Group

ECDC EPIET Fellow (Sept. 2018 - Sept. 2020)

Supervisor: Dr Katharina Alpers

European Field Epidemiology Training Programme (FETP), see ECDC EPIET below

- National infectious disease surveillance
- Public health research
- Outbreak investigation, including the COVID-19 outbreak response in Germany
- Communication & teaching: social media for public health

# **European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control (ECDC)**

Sept 2018 - Sept 2020, Europe

Fellow of the European Programme for Intervention Epidemiology Training (EPIET)

Supervisors: Dr Adam Roth & Dr Louise Coole

- Visiting scientist at the Luxembourg Institute of Health
- Cohort Representative (elected): spokesperson and point of contact for fellows, the ECDC Fellowship programme heads, the training site forum, and the EPIET Alumni
- Full portfolio on the ECDC website

Last updated: April 2022

# **World Health Organization (WHO)**

# Western Pacific Regional Office, Division of Pacific Technical Support

December 2019 - January 2020, Suva, Fiji

**Epidemiologist** 

Supervisors: Dr Angela Merianos, Mr Sean Casey

Short-term consultant / GOARN (Global Outbreak Alert and Response Network) deployment.

 Provided technical and operational assistance to Pacific Ministries of Health, for strengthening measles surveillance and other outbreak response activities, in Pacific Island Countries.

# **Stichting HIV Monitoring [Dutch HIV Monitoring Foundation]**

February 2016 - June 2018, Amsterdam, the Netherlands

Epidemiologist & Postdoctoral Researcher

Supervisor: Prof dr Peter Reiss

National HIV surveillance and monitoring of HIV treatment and quality of care in the Netherlands.

- Routine epidemiological data analysis of clinical HIV data; periodical reporting of the descriptive epidemiology of the HIV epidemic
- Analysis, dissemination and communication of healthcare performance indicators of all 26 HIV treatment centres in the Netherlands
- Provide technical support, methodological advice, and data analysis support for research proposals submitted by treatment centres
- Advise and support data management and monitoring in the improvement of data collection protocols, standardisation of data processing, and data quality control.
- Conduct clinical epidemiological and methodological research on the HIV epidemic
- Participate in international collaborations: University College London, Institute for Global Health, International Cohort Consortium of Infectious Diseases (RESPOND); Harvard Program on Causal Inference, HIV-CAUSAL
- Student supervision (MSc and PhD level)

# Amsterdam Institute for Global Health and Development | Department of Global Health, Academic Medical Centre of the University of Amsterdam

February 2013 - January 2016, Amsterdam, the Netherlands

PhD Fellow

Supervisor: Prof dr Tobias Rinke de Wit

- Surveillance and monitoring of HIV treatment in adults and children in sub-Saharan Africa, in 13 public and private clinical sites, from six countries.
- Provide technical support and guidance to strengthen the surveillance system for HIV drug resistance in sub-Saharan Africa
- Expert Consultant for the WHO HIV ResNet (lead: Dr SIIvia Bertagnolio), the global network advising WHO on the control and surveillance of HIV drug resistance:
  - Provide technical assistance for strengthening HIV drug resistance surveillance in resource-limited settings
  - Contributed to the development of the WHO 'Global Action Plan on HIV Drug Resistance, 2017-2021' and the 'HIV Drug Resistance Report 2017'

 Conducted a WHO commissioned literature-review and meta-analysis (Boender et. al; CID 2015)

VU University Amsterdam, Department of Health Sciences
Division of Infectious Diseases | Division of Methodology & Applied Biostatistics
April 2012 - February 2013, Amsterdam, the Netherlands

Lecturer

Supervisor: Dr Maiza Campos Ponce

- Teaching in lectures and work-groups, supervise research internships
- Support, plan and organise lectures and tutorials, manage and train course assistants

#### **ADDITIONAL ACTIVITIES**

- Advocate for science communication training academics and epidemiologists in social media for public health #SoMe4epi, #VaccineEmoji
- Guest/invited lecturer in applied infectious disease epidemiology and international public health, at the VU University Amsterdam, Leiden University College, TU Eindhoven, Berlin School of Public Health, European Centre for Disease Prevention & Control, 3-5 lectures/year, since 2013.
- Active member of the EPIET Alumni Network (EAN)
- Active member of the Dutch Society for Epidemiology
  - Co-founder of the Special Interest Group 'Applied Infectious Disease Epidemiology' with the Dutch Society for Epidemiology
- Review Editor for Research Methods and Advances in Epidemiology
- Statistical Reviewer for The Lancet journals (open access only)

#### **COMPUTER SKILLS**

- Proficient in R, STATA, SAS, SPSS, EpiData, Adobe Pro, GraphPad Prism, MS Office
- Experienced with GIT, Epilnfo, KoboCollect, Nvivo, MS Access, QGIS/ArcGIS, Adobe Creative Suite (Photoshop, InDesign, Illustrator).

### PROFESSIONAL REGISTRATIONS

- Infodemic Manager (certificate of training), WHO and partners, June 2021
- UN/WHO online training: OpenWHO Introduction: Operational Readiness (Tier 1), Incident Management System (Tier 1), WHO GOARN training, The Global Outbreak Alert and Response Network (GOARN), Working with GOARN in the Field, UNDSS BSAFE
- Senior Epidemiologist, Registered with the Dutch Society for Epidemiology
- Field Epidemiologist (advanced-level): ECDC EPIET
- ICH Good clinical practice (ICH-GCP) certified

#### **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS**

Also see my full list of research publications (>35), conferences proceedings, invited talks, and science communication activities <a href="https://www.soniaboender.com">www.soniaboender.com</a>

- Using routine emergency department data for syndromic surveillance of acute respiratory illness before and during the COVID-19 pandemic in Germany, week 10-2017 to 10-2021.
  - <u>Boender TS</u>, Cai W, Schranz M, Kocher T, Wagner B, Ullrich A, Buda S, Zöllner R, Greiner F, Diercke M, Grabenhenrich L. Eurosurveillance (accepted for publication), see preprint on medRxiv
- Digital Visual Communication for Public Health: Design Proposal for a Vaccinated Emoji.
  - <u>Boender TS</u>, Louis-Ferdinand N, Duschek G. J Med Internet Res 2022;24(4):e35786. doi: 10.2196/35786
- Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic and associated non-pharmaceutical interventions on other notifiable infectious diseases in Germany: An analysis of national surveillance data during week 1-2016 - week 32-2020.
  - Ullrich A, Schranz M, Rexroth U, Hamouda O, Schaade L, Diercke M, <u>Boender TS</u>; Robert Koch's Infectious Disease Surveillance Group.
  - Lancet Reg Health Eur. 2021 Jun 19;6:100103. doi: 10.1016/j.lanepe.2021.100103
- Social media for field epidemiologists (#SoMe4Epi): How to use Twitter during the #COVID19 pandemic.
  - Hammer CC, <u>Boender TS</u>, Thomas DR. Int J Infect Dis. 2021 May 19:S1201-9712(21)00437-9. doi: 10.1016/j.ijid.2021.05.035
- Acute hepatitis C infection among adults with HIV in the Netherlands between 2003 and 2016: a capture-recapture analysis for the 2013 to 2016 period.
   Boender TS, Op de Coul E, Arends J, Prins M, van der Valk M, van der Meer JTM, van Benthem B, Reiss P, Smit C. Euro Surveill. 2020 Feb;25(7). doi: 10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2020.25.7.1900450
- Pretreatment HIV drug resistance increases regimen switches in sub-Saharan Africa.
   <u>Boender TS</u>, Hoenderboom BM, Sigaloff KC, Hamers RL, Wellington M, Shamu T,
   Siwale M, Labib Maksimos EE, Nankya I, Kityo CM, Adeyemo TA, Akanmu AS,
   Mandaliya K, Botes ME, Ondoa P, Rinke de Wit TF.
   Clin Infect Dis. 2015 Dec 1;61(11):1749-58. doi: 10.1093/cid/civ656